Guide to the Society for Clinical Surgery Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Society of Clinical Surgery records
1903-1998
MS 1267
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.25
The records consist of correspondence, minutes, membership lists, programs, reports, and photographs which document the founding of the Society of Clinical Surgery, as well as its meetings from 1903-1998. The records also include histories of the society by Harvey Cushing, Harris B. Shumacker, Jr., and Wiley Barker.
Society of Clinical Surgery
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical Library, 1980, and gift of the Society of Clinical Surgery, 1992 and 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Society of Clinical Surgery consist of correspondence, minutes, lists of members, programs, reports, and photographs, which document the founding of the Society, as well as its meetings from 1903 until the 1990s. The records also include histories of the Society.
Some records of the Society were transferred to Manuscripts and Archives in 1980 from the Medical Historical Library. These records appear to have been collected to some extent by Harvey Cushing, who served as president of the Society and who wrote a history of the Society's founding. The Society gave additional records to the department in 1992 and in 2004. Some of these records were collected by Harris B. Shumacker, Jr. for his history of the Society.
The records are arranged in sections: Correspondence, Histories, Meetings, and Membership. Correspondence includes exchanges between members on organizational and historical matters from the beginning of the Society until 1977. Most of the correspondence is loose and arranged in chronological order. Folder 1, however, contains a bound volume of the earliest correspondence. Manuscript drafts, illustrations, and printed copies of the Cushing and Shumacker histories of the Society are filed under Histories, while bibliographies of members and printed membership rosters and biographies of members, published with the Society's constitution, are found filed under Membership.
The bulk of the records is arranged under Meetings. This material includes meeting registers and at least one folder of material for meetings of the Society, from its 1st in 1903 through its 134th in 1977, with the exception of the 64th, 76th, 92nd, 121st, or 131st meetings. Folders may contain the meeting program, minutes from the meeting, reports, photographs, and memorabilia. For the 40th meeting, held in 1925 in Europe, there are annotated photograph albums and negatives matching the prints in them. No meetings were held between the 74th in 1942 and the 75th in 1946. A war report of the Society is filed between the folders for these two meetings. At the end of this section, in folders 169-175, there are bound volumes containing minutes, reports, and programs. While most of the material in these volumes is printed and duplicates materials in the files for individual meetings, volumes in folders 169-170 contain typed copies of minutes. An addition to the collection is similarly arranged.
Biographical / Historical
The Society of Clinical Surgery was founded in 1903 as a travel club for young surgeons. Charter members included James G. Mumford, George E. Brewer, Harvey Cushing, Charles H. Frazier, George W. Crile, and John C. Munro.
The activities of the Society are directed toward the general advancement of surgery. The Society seeks to stimulate its members to work along lines of original thought and investigation in the clinic, laboratory, or library and to develop and improve methods of surgical teaching.
The size of the Society's membership is deliberately kept small. Members are elected and must be between the ages of thirty and fifty-five. They must have an official connection with some medical institution, whether school, hospital or laboratory.
Through its meetings the Society affords members opportunities to demonstrate advances in operative methods and surgical teaching. Meeting hosts arrange presentations and demonstrations at their institutions to help keep members abreast of current surgical ideas and techniques. The meetings also include dinners and receptions, which provide time for socializing.
Though meetings have been held primarily in the United States, a few meetings were held abroad and offered surgeons the opportunity for foreign travel. Until 1974 the Society usually met twice a year. Then, the Society adopted a policy of single annual meetings.
Medicine; Surgery; Barker, Wiley F.; Crile, George Washington, 1864-1943; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Frazier, Charles H. (Charles Harrison), 1870-1936; Shumacker, Harris B., 1908-; Society of Clinical Surgery
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1903-1942, 1944-1951, 1953, 1959, 1964, 1970-1975, 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 18)
  - Histories
    - History of the Society
      - Report, Pre-1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Illustrations, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Illustrations, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Printed copy, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Additional materials, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "The Society of Clinical Surgery in Retrospect"
      - Manuscript, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 24 - 25)
      - Printed copy, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Meetings
    - Meeting register, 1903-1969 (Box 2, Folder 27 - 28)
    - 1st-11th, 1903-1908 (Box 2, Folder 29 - 40)
    - 12th-20th, 1909-1913 (Box 3, Folder 41 - 51)
    - 20th: photograph (Box 14)
    - 21st-38th, 1913-1924 (Box 3, Folder 52 - 70)
    - 39th, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - 40th
      - Report, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 72)
      - Photographs, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 73 - 74)
      - Photograph album, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 75 - 76)
      - Photograph album: negatives, 1925 (Box 5)
      - Program and menus, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - 41st-58th, 1925-1934 (Box 6, Folder 78 - 95)
    - 59th-74th, 1934-1942 (Box 7, Folder 96 - 110)
    - War report, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - 75th, 77th, 78th, 1946-1948 (Box 7, Folder 112 - 114)
    - 79th-91st, 93rd-108th, 1948-1963 (Box 8, Folder 115 - 143)
    - 109th-120th, 122nd-130th, 132nd-134th, 1963-1977 (Box 9, Folder 144 - 167)
    - Unidentified: photograph, undated (Box 9, Folder 168)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1903-1920 (Box 10, Folder 169 - 170)
    - Minutes and pictures, 1967-1973 (Box 10, Folder 171)
    - Programs and minutes of meetings, 1903-1923 (Box 11, Folder 172 - 175)
  - Membership
    - Statistics and constitution, 1906, 1913, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 176 - 178)
    - Statistics, 1923 (Box 12, Folder 179)
    - Constitution and statistics, 1928, 1933, 1940, 1949, 1959, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 180 - 185)
    - Membership, constitution and statistics, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 186)
    - Bibliography of members, 1906-1909 (Box 12, Folder 187)
- Additional Material, Accession 2005-M-019
  Scope and Contents
  This addition to the Society of Clinical Surgery Records mirrors the arrangement of the original material: correspondence, histories, meetings, and membership, arranged chronologically within a category. There is some overlap in the Meetings files from the 1909 meeting (#12) through the 1977 meeting (#134) with the original material. This accession then continues with the 1978 meeting (#135) and continues through the 1990s.
  - Correspondence
    - 1972-1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Histories
    - Barker, Wiley, History of the Society of Clinical Surgery
      - Draft, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Handwritten notes on clinic visits in Europe, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Meetings
    - 12th, 13th, 16th, 17th, 20th-22nd, 24th-31st, 34th, 35th, 42nd, 43rd, 69th, 1909 April-1939 November (Box 1, Folder 8 - 27)
    - War Report, no. 1, 1942 November (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 100th, 108th-111th, 1959 May-1964 October (Box 1, Folder 29 - 33)
    - 112th-119th, 1965 April-1969 April (Box 2, Folder 34 - 41)
    - 120th-129th, 1969 October-1974 May (Box 3, Folder 42 - 51)
    - 130th-143rd, 1974 October-1986 November (Box 4, Folder 52 - 65)
    - 144th-148th, 1987 November-1991 November (Box 5, Folder 66 - 70)
    - 149th, 151st, 1992 November, 1994 November (Box 6, Folder 71 - 72)
    - Executive Council meeting, 1997 April (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - 155th, 1998 November (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Log of meeting announcements, 1987-1992 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Membership
    - Applications, membership lists, 1992-1997 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Membership lists, biographies, and related photographs, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Constitution and statistics, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Financial information, 1985-1990 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Mailing list, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Photographs, 1953-1967, undated (Box 6, Folder 81)